Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Refugees and Forced Migration, 2001 -- 2012; UA197.008; 23 Digital Object(s)
    - Invisible in Thailand: Tufts-International Rescue Committee Survey of Burmese Migrants in Thailand, 2008-04-25; UA197.008.008.00004; Green-Rauerhorst, Margaret; Jacobsen, Karen; Pyne, Sandee
      The International Rescue Committee (IRC) is concerned that there are significant numbers of Burmese living in Thailand who qualify for and deserve international protection and assistance even though they do not have access to proper registration processes. Without a transparent, humane and lawful asylum policy for Burmese people entering Thailand, it is impossible to estimate the percentage of bona fide refugees that are mixed into the group of migrants who have left Burma solely for other reasons. The lack of systematic data to document the reasons people flee Burma provides the Thai authorities with the excuse to treat the Burmese living outside the refugee camps as mere economic migrants, subject to deportation. It also weakens the leverage that agencies working with the Burmese living in Thailand have to advocate on their behalf.
      Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - Internal Displacement to Urban Areas: the Tufts-IDMC Profiling Study (Khartoum, Sudan), 2008-08-27; UA197.008.008.00005; Jacobsen, Karen
      In recent decades Sudan's North-South civil war and the Conflict, Armed (War) in Darfur have generated one of the largest internally displaced populations in the world. A large proportion of these IDPs is found in and around the capital, Khartoum. The Tufts-IDMC study of Khartoum was a pilot for our larger study and was carried out in 2007, two years after the signing of the Comprehensive Peace Agreement. While the CPA raised hopes for the return of IDPs, continuing insecurity, lack of services in areas of return and doubts about the sustainability of the CPA, have slowed the pace of return.
    - Microcredit and other loan programs in protracted refugee situations: Lessons from the Alchemy Project, 2008-11-15; UA197.008.008.00006; Jacobsen, Karen
      We are very pleased to share with you this working document. In the interests of exploring livelihood interventions that could support the financial resilience of refugees and IDPs, the Feinstein International Center is pleased to make available a paper titled "Microcredit and other loan programs in protracted refugee situations: Lessons from the Alchemy Project." The paper is a working document, intended for practitioners, and discussion and comments are encouraged. The author, Jacobsen, Karen, welcomes and encourages feedback, which will be incorporated into new drafts and commentary, then posted on our website.
      Refugees; Conflict, Armed (War); Economies and societies in transition; Feinstein International Center
    - Internal Displacement to Urban Areas: the Tufts-IDMC Profiling Study (Santa Marta, Columbia), 2008-09-03; UA197.008.008.00007; Jacobsen, Karen; Howe, Kimberly
      For more than 40 years, Colombians have been subject to chronic violence perpetrated by left-wing guerillas, paramilitaries, government forces, and drug cartels. In the past 20 years, an estimated four million people have been forced to leave their homes. Generally, the pattern of Forced Human beings--Migrations has been within rural areas or to small administrative centers or larger cities. More recently, this pattern has changed, with Forced Human beings--Migrations occurring within city limits or between city centers. This new pattern of intra-urban Forced Human beings--Migrations has been notable since the Conflict, Armed (War) began to become 'urbanized' (primarily in Medellin and Bogota) from around 2000, leading to new forms of Conflict, Armed (War) and social tension in urban areas.
    - African Migration to Israel: Debt, Employment and Remittances, 2011-02-07; UA197.008.008.00008; Furst-Nichols, Rebecca; Jacobsen, Karen
      This report details the migration experience and livelihood choices of Sudanese and Eritrean asylum seekers and migrants in Tel Aviv. The research is based on a scoping study conducted by a Feinstein Researcher, Rebecca Furst-Nichols, in November-December 2010. Since 2007, an increasing number of African migrants and asylum seekers have been smuggled across the Egyptian Sinai into Israel. Today, there are nearly 35,000 non-Jewish African migrants living in Israel, the majority Eritrean and Sudanese. The report provides an overview of Israeli policy toward African migrants and asylum seekers, routes taken to Israel, experience with Bedouin smugglers, employment opportunities, legal status, protection issues, and the role of remittances in repaying smuggling debt to family and friends in the diaspora.
    - 2004 Intern Report (Alchemy Project), 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00009; Davis, Joy-Dee
      My internship in the Democratic Republic of Congo lasted from June 1st to August 12th 2004. I was attached to the Jesuit Refugee Services. Owing to the civil unrest that have besieged the Congo, I was stranded in Europe from 1st to 9th June and therefore did not arrive in Kinshasa until June 9th 2004. Fearing the outbreak of more hostilities I made an attempt to conduct my interviews speedily.
      Refugees; Internally displaced persons; Feinstein International Center
    - African States and the Politics of Refugees: Refugee Assistance as Political Resources, 2002-01-25; UA197.008.008.00010; Jacobsen, Karen
      Mass influxes of refugees are widely held to be one more intractable problem for impoverished and conflict-ridden African countries -- "a luxury [the world's poorest states] .. can no longer afford" as a recent text put it (UNHCR 1998: 71). Refugees are seen to impose a variety of economic and environmental burdens on host countries, and to create or aggravate security threats. However, for the past twenty years, refugee flows have also been accompanied by a significant resource transfer in the form of international humanitarian assistance and human capital. Refugee camps have become the repositories of such resources as relief supplies and food aid, vehicles, communication equipment, and other locally valued and scarce materials. The refugees themselves bring human capital in the form of labor, skills and education. In addition, refugees are, if only for a brief burst of international media attention, a highly visible phenomenon, capable of focusing attention on regions normally lost to the public eye. They therefore represent political leverage for savvy actors in the region. Thus, a sustained injection of material, social and political 'refugee resources' is suddenly available in a receiving region. In most African host countries, however, refugee hosting areas are poor and underdeveloped, and commonly experience increased security problems with a refugee influx.
    - Alchemy Field Report on FCC Micro Credit Programs to Refugees in Mozambique, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00011; Omata, Naohiko
      This paper is a report by an Alchemy intern at Fundo de Credito Communtario (FCC) in Mozambique for the summer of 2004. The report consists of five sections. The first section briefly outlines the current environment surrounding refugees in Mozambique and the refugee policy of Mozambican government. The next section explains micro credit lending program of FCC in Mozambique, with emphasis on its Refugee Integration Program (RIP), as well as FCC's lending stance in its program. In the third section, the paper evaluates the impact of FCC's micro credit lending program in Maputo based on the latest results of Alchemy interviews with FCC RIP clients and non-clients. Then, it presents recommendation and proposals for FCC and concludes with prospective direction of FCC.
      Refugees; Microfinance.; Feinstein International Center
    - Alchemy Project Bibliography, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00012; Jacobsen, Karen
      Bibliography of relevant documents for the Alchemy Project
    - Alchemy Project Field Assessment, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00013; Morarji, Maitri
      In June – July 2004, Maitri Morarji, a 2005 MALD Candidate at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University (Boston, USA), conducted an impact assessment of Arid Lands Development Focus's (ALDEF) credit and savings program in Wajir, Kenya. Over a seven-week period, in-depth interviews were conducted with 49 individual women borrowers from ALDEF's credit and savings program, and with 10 non-borrowers, constituting the control group. The interviewer utilized an income support and livelihoods baseline instrument developed by the Alchemy Project, as well as numerous informal information-gathering sessions to determine what impact the credit program has on promoting livelihood and food security among internally displaced women in Wajir town and its outskirts.
    - Alchemy Project: Johannesburg, South Africa Summer 2004 Report, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00014; Lukoma, Josephine F.
      This report is a compilation of research on the micro credit environment and micro credit services available to urban refugees in Johannesburg, South Africa; field research was conducted between June and August 2004. I conducted this research as an Alchemy Project intern based in the Johannesburg offices of the Jesuit Refugee Services (JRS) which is an implementing partner of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees. The Alchemy Project based at the Alan Shawn Feinstein International Famine Centre at Tufts University, situated in Medford, MA, USA, focuses its research on ways of enabling refugees and Internally Displaced Persons (IDPs) to re-establish their livelihoods in African host countries and communities. The Alchemy Project provides capital for loans to local partners who are providing micro credit services to IDPs and refugees. In exchange the local partners participate in the research process of the project through data collection activities and the feedback they give to Alchemy staff on their programs. The research presented here was conducted among urban refugees, refugee service providers and local microfinance institutions (MFIs) in Johannesburg. All data collected is accessible at the Alchemy Project offices.
    - Alchemy Project: Report for Field Visit with Cord in Zambia, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00015; Titus, Sarah
      The overarching purpose of the Alchemy Project's site visit to our partner organization CORD (Christian Outreach, Relief and Development) in Zambia was to collect data on its micro-credit program and other income generating and livelihood support programs, provide technical assistance and work with the organization to establish a baseline survey instrument that will be used on an ongoing basis to monitor and evaluate the micro-credit program currently operating in Nangweshi refugee camp. The Alchemy Project sent graduate student intern Sarah Titus to the field in June to conduct interviews and focus groups and begin laying the foundation for instillation of the monitoring and evaluation instrument.
    - Alchemy Report on World Relief's Income Generation Animal Husbandry Program, 2005-04-06; UA197.008.008.00016; Mecagni, Anna
      Mozambique is a host country for approximately 10,130 refugees.1 A majority of these refugees, approximately 5,000, live in a refugee camp in the northern region of Nampula. The Maratane Refugee Camp lies in a rural area about 20 km away from Nampula, the third largest city in Mozambique and the informal capital of the northern region of Mozambique. Other significant populations of refugees, more than 4,000, live in major cities including Maputo, the capital city, Nampula, Lichinga, among others. There are a few skilled refugees, including teachers and nurses, who have been sent by the government to other regions of Mozambique to work in their particular professions, as there is a lack of skilled Mozambicans in these fields.
    - FIFC Working Papers from R&FMP and Alchemy Program, 2004-07-01; UA197.008.008.00017; Feinstein International Center
      Summaries of working papers on the subjects of refugees, forced migration, and microfinance (2002-2004).
      Refugees; David Sussman; Sarah Bailey; Jodie Fonseca; Stacy Michelle Heen; Jeffrey Isen; Katherine Robinson; Feinstein International Center
    - Final Report: Alchemy Internship with ARC/IGP Sierra Leone, 2005-03-07; UA197.008.008.00018; Buckius, Elizabeth
      American Refugee Committee's Income Generation Program (ARC/IGP) was established in Sierra Leone at the end of 2003 as a part of the Microenterprise/Income Generation Program (MED/IGP) of American Refugee Committee International (ARC). ARC/Sierra Leone's (ARC/SL) headquarters are located in Freetown. The office for ARC/IGP, however, is in Kenema, which is the third largest city in Sierra Leone, located in Kenema District, Eastern Province. ARC/IGP is active in four of the eight neighboring refugee camps for Liberian refugees. These include: Jembe, Gerihun, Largo and Tobanda with populations of: 7,337; 6,806; 6,764; and 7,208, respectively. These numbers are from March 2004, when a re-verification was conducted by UNHCR because many Liberian refugees were self-repatriating around the beginning of the year. This re-verification calculates that 24,819 people spontaneously repatriated between October 2003 and February 2004.
    - Microfinance in protracted refugee situations: Lessons from the Alchemy Project, 2004-07-23; UA197.008.008.00019; Jacobsen, Karen
      The problem of how to support refugees1 and other forcibly displaced people in protracted situations continues to challenge aid agencies. A protracted refugee situation is one in which refugees have been 'stuck' for a period of time2 beyond their initial displacement, where they are unable to return to their homes, and no solutions to their predicament are in sight. One of the defining characteristics of protracted refugee situations is the rapid decline in the supply of humanitarian assistance, including food aid. Agencies now increasingly recognize the need to support the efforts of displaced people to pursue their own livelihoods, but there are few resources available. Aid agencies have experimented with interventions such as income generating or cash-forwork programs, but these are often the first programs to be cut, and in general they are not well resourced, understood or evaluated.
      Microfinance.; Refugees; Internally displaced persons; Feinstein International Center
    - Refugee Youth and Community in Boston: Negotiating School and Community Relations, 2003-10-22; UA197.008.008.00020; Raven Roberts, Angela
      Boston is a major resettlement city for many refugees coming from crisis and war affected countries around the world. One of the major issues that face refugee families in their acculturation and resettlement process in the city is how to give meaningful support and attention to the special needs and factors that affect their youth as they settle into a different school and cultural environment. The meeting brought together participants representing refugee organizations, community leaders, teachers, foster parents, academics and research institutes based in Boston.
    - Refugee Youth in Boston: Negotiating School and Community Relations, 2003-03-12; UA197.008.008.00021; Feinstein International Center
      Flyer for a workshop sponsored by the Feinstein International Famine Center and the Tufts University Children's Center.
      Raven-Roberts, Angela, 1949-; Feinstein International Center
    - Report on Workshop: Refugee Resettlement and Education in New England, 2003-10-22; UA197.008.008.00022; Raven Roberts, Angela
      The objective of the meeting was to host a two-day meeting to discuss the educational and social needs of refugee youth being re-settled in the Boston area. Participants were invited from a number of resettlement and refugee welfare agencies in the Boston and Portland regions as well as teachers, youth workers, volunteers and representatives from refugee community organizations. In addition we were joined by representatives of refugee sending organizations in East Africa. Key highlights of the meeting included the active participation of and presentations by a number of youth from the Boston and Portland area.
    - The Role of Buddhist Institutions in the Tibetan Disapora, 2001-09-24; UA197.008.008.00023; Gellek, Tsering
      The purpose of this paper is to examine the socioeconomic impact of Tibetan Buddhist institutions on the Tibetan diasporic community. From monasteries, to the institution of the office of the Dalai Lama1, to the pervasive system of religious patronage, Buddhism is incorporated into all aspects of Tibetan life and customs. For many Tibetan refugees religion has served as the all-encompassing motivation, foundation, and path, into exile and survival.
      Buddhism; Diasporas; Refugees; Feinstein International Center
    - UWESO Internally Displaced Persons Income Generating and Capacity Building Project, 2004-12-21; UA197.008.008.00024; Kembabazi, Jane; Ogbamichael, Huria
      As part of the Refugee and Forced Migration Program the Alchemy Field Project funds and conducts research on educational and micro-finance opportunities for refugees and internally displaced persons in African countries. In 2004 the program decided to extend its activities to Uganda where it received a proposal for a micro-finance project from Uganda Women's efforts to Save Orphans (for more details on UWESO see below) After agreement had been reached on the cooperation with the partner organization the University decided to send to interns to Northern Uganda in the summer of 2004 to conduct a baseline survey for the newly approved micro-finance project in the IDP camps of Lira town. The aim of this report is to provide the Refugee and Forced Migration Program as well as the partner organization with an assessment of the initial phase of the project.
    - Developing a Profiling Methodology for Displaced People in Urban Areas, 2012-01-09; UA197.008.008.00025; Jacobsen, Karen; Furst Nichols, Rebecca
      In seeking to develop effective programmatic interventions, it is useful for humanitarian agencies to understand whether displaced people in urban areas are worse off than the urban poor and other migrants amongst whom they live. There is controversy around this issue. A widely held belief is that refugees and IDPs are worse off in urban settings, because they have lost their assets and social networks, and lack secure housing, land and property rights, and the cultural knowledge required to survive in a city. Others have argued that refugees are not necessarily more vulnerable than other migrants, and these differences are eroded over time. In particular, some research suggests that international migrants, including refugees, are often better equipped to deal with cities than newly urbanized citizens of the host country. Whether refugees and IDPs are more economically vulnerable and at greater risk is one of the questions we explore in this research.
    - Remittances to Transit Countries, 2012-10-01; UA197.008.008.00026; Jacobsen, Karen; Ayoub, Maysa; Johnson, Alice; One important gap in the literature on refugees' and international migrants' remittances concerns flows between developing countries. "South-South" flows, particularly those to and from transit countries in the vicinity of conflict zones have not been researched. Transit countries are those that become way stations or stopping points in the journey from origin to intended destination countries. In the east of the African continent, Egypt and Kenya are countries of first asylum for Sudanese and Somalis, but also transit settings for refugees and other migrants seeking to migrate to Europe, North America or the Gulf.
      Egypt; Migration; Refugees; Emigrant remittances; Feinstein International Center
  - Livelihood Programming for Disaster Risk Reduction, 2010; UA197.009; 2 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Livelihood Programming for Disaster Risk Reduction project.
    - Baseline Report: Africa Community Resilience Project (Tsaeda Amba Woreda, Eastern Tigray, Ethiopia), 2010-01-06; UA197.009.009.00001; Maxwell, Daniel; Tadesse, Girum; Mukwavi, Mary; Hailu, Shimelis; Zewold, Wolde Gebreal; Gebrekiros, Abraha
      Disaster Risk Reduction (DRR) programs encompass many different kinds of activities, but share the fundamental objective of enhancing the capacity of vulnerable communities to identify, reduce and manage risk, whether it be at the local, regional or national level. Ethiopia is one of the most food-insecure countries in the world, but only recently has the Food security problem begun to be understood in terms of a complete analysis of livelihoods, rather than simply a food supply problem.
      Food security; Disaster relief--Developing countries; Feinstein International Center
    - Increasing the Financial Resilience of Disaster-affected Populations, 2010-02-26; UA197.009.009.00002; Jacobsen, Karen; Marshak, Anastasia; Griffith, Matthew
      Increasing the Financial Resilience of Disaster-affected Populations is a desk review paper commissioned and supported by the Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance, USAID. One of the most significant problems facing a disaster-affected population is the need for ready cash. In a post-disaster context cash is difficult to come by for a variety of reasons. A useful approach then, to enable recovery and reduce risk, is to identify effective ways to enable households to access (or hold onto) a lump sum of ready cash. This paper outlines the meaning of household financial resilience and its relationship to the household's cash position. It then explores the impact of different kinds of hazards on the cash position of affected households and how different approaches - both existing humanitarian assistance and livelihood ones, and recent innovations - have addressed financial resilience, drawing on a range of case studies. The paper specifically highlights insurance, savings, and credit as a means by which households can raise a lump sum and sure up their financial resilience.
      Disaster relief--Developing countries; Feinstein International Center
  - Livelihoods Change Over Time, 2010 -- 2012; UA197.010; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Livelihoods Change Over Time project.
    - Institutional Assessment Report: Tsaeda Amba Woreda, Eastern Tigray, Ethiopia, 2010-06-22; UA197.010.010.00001; Coates, Jennifer; Maxwell, Daniel; Tadesse, Girum; Hailu, Shimelis; Nugussie, Woldegebrial Zeweld; Gebrekiros, Abraha
      Based on data collected in January 2010 through focus groups and household-level interviews in Tsaeda Amba woreda, this assessment depicts the breadth of institutional constraints to risk reduction and livelihood security. Major areas of findings include access to land and natural resources, credit and the risks of default, and traditional practices and institutions. While a participatory baseline assessment, published in December 2009, focused mostly on forms of covariate risk and the measures proposed the ACRP to address them, this second report highlights more idiosyncratic forms of risk.
      Economies and societies in transition; Feinstein International Center
    - Examining Linkages between Disaster Risk Reduction and Livelihoods (Literature Review), 2011-02-23; UA197.010.010.00002; Feinstein International Center